# 你看你看这个豆皮
Check out the skin of the white kidney beans.
# 忽扇忽扇的动 活了
It flaps as if it's alive.
# 这就是宫里边的一个养生菜品
This is a nourishing dish originated from Chinese imperial cuisine.
# 你看看烂不烂
Look how mushy it is.
# 小骨头秃噜秃噜全出来了
The little bones come out so smoothly.
# Empress Mother Pork Feet
# 为什么叫老佛爷猪手啊
Why is it called empress mother pork feet?
# 你看这料 猪蹄儿 红枣 大芸豆 当归
Take a look at the ingredients, pork feet, red dates, big white kidney beans and dong quai.
# 虽说料简单 每天三个枣 长寿还不老
Though they are just simple ingredients, we always say three dates a day keeps the doctor away.
# 大爷您看看 这个猪手
Da Ye, for these pork feet,
# 再干净我也得燎燎
no matter how clean they look, I'll still have to singe them.
# 燎一燎还有去腥的作用 去腥增香
The singeing process can also help remove the stinky smell. - And enhance the aroma.
# 烧一下皮 它出来这个味道会更好
It tastes better after being singed on the skin.
# 焦香味 这猪蹄必须得上火
I smell the browning aroma. These pork feet must go through this process with fire.
# 大爷您知道那时候干加工间的时候
You know, Da Ye, when I was working in the processing room,
# 猪手一片 大猪头
there were pork feet everywhere, as well as the huge pig’s heads.
# 天天的那一片 满地的加工间
We did this everyday in the processing room with these pork stuff everywhere.
# 拿喷灯整个喷 可累了那时候
We used a blowtorch to blow at every bit of the pork. That was so exhausting.
# 现在都先进了师父
We have more advanced method now, master.
# 这小气罐可好使了
The little gas can works like magic.
# 你们这都说的都是先进了
Yeah what you are talking about is much more advanced.
# 我们刚上班拿一个钢叉子
When we just started working, we would hold a big steel fork,
# 一叉 拿那火燎
thrust the fork into the pork, then singe it on fire.
# 我宁愿选择费事儿
I would rather go through that trouble
# 也得要保持传统手法
to keep food cooked with our traditional methods.
# 这个头这块儿 爪尖这缝隙这
This end, the gap between the toes.
# 把它烧透了 基本这味道就没了
Once you have this spot singed thoroughly, you’ve basically got rid of the stink.
# 这回行了 这回没啥问题了
It’s good now. No problem this time.
# 二伯是一个做事做菜认真的人
Er Bai is very serious with cooking and everything.
# 好啦 泡一会儿 温水
The singeing is done. Let’s soak it in warm water for a little while.
# 来 我刷
Let me do the brushing.
# 拿钢丝棉球一擦就倍儿漂亮
It’ll look very nice after being brushed by the stainless steel scourer.
# 大爷您知道
Da Ye, do you know
# 您此时此刻您想说什么话啊
what you would like to say right now?
# 知道么大爷 我不知道
Do you, Da Ye? - No, I don’t.
# 不知道我知道
I do.
# 有徒弟真好
It’s so nice to have an apprentice.
# 特别简单 拿钢丝球咔咔咔一蹭
It’s super simple, just scratch it with the stainless steel scourer.
# 你说这烧出来能不好吃吗
It’s impossible for it to not taste good after being singed like this,
# 就这道工序
with this kind of process.
# 看看这猪蹄刮洗干净 多干净
Now the pork feet have been scratched and washed. - They are super clean.
# 倍儿漂亮
It looks awesome.
# 刚才烧那么黑 现在这么漂亮
The pork feet were so blackened, but now look so brilliant.
# 就这个工序太重要了
This procedure is very important.
# 咱先给它出出水吧
Let’s parboil it first.
# 凉水下锅
We start with cold water.
# 咱先出着水 我得把白豆煮出来
We leave it parboiling there. Now I’m gonna cook the white kidney beans.
# 桂皮 大料 小茴香
Cinnamon, star anise and fennel seed.
# 把豆煮了它 主要是为了入味
We cook the beans mainly for the flavor penetration.
# 小茴香 大料 桂皮
Fennel seed, star anise and cinnamon.
# 这芸豆是昨天晚上泡好的 那好熟
The white kidney beans were soaked since last night. - Then that makes it easy to be cooked.
# 这有个一刻钟 二十分钟足矣了
Probably 15 minutes would be enough, at most 20 minutes.
# 实际上亮子 不管什么样的干货
Actually, Liang Zi, no matter what kind of dried product,
# 前期用凉水泡 涨发这个环节很重要
it’s very important to have them soaked in cold water beforehand, and let them re-hydrate.
# 一定要让它
You have to
# 慢慢的吸收水分 慢慢的回软
let it gradually absorb water and become soft.
# 等你煮的时候就特别快了
It really boosts the speed of cooking.
# 现煮煮一小时也煮不烂
If you cook it without the preparation, then even cooking for one hour wouldn’t be enough for it to become soft.
# 差不多了 来点酒
It’s about time to put some cooking wine in.
# 还一样东西呢
Still an ingredient to go,
# 搁了两片当归
which is two pieces of dong quai.
# 大爷你看见没有
Da Ye, have you seen that
# 小亮子洗得多干净 一点浮沫没有
Liang Zi have cleaned the pork feet so well. There isn’t any bit of scum.
# 这个猪蹄泡好了 燎完了之后一出水
After being soaked, singed and then parboiled,
# 基本上吐不出什么沫了
these pork feet basically wouldn’t be able to generate any scum.
# 直接端这边冲水吧
Let’s carry it over here to have a rinse.
# 不要原汤 原汤有燎了毛的味
Do not continue to use the water used for parboiling, because it has the smell of singeing hair.
# 行了调个汤
Awesome. Let’s cook the soup.
# 葱姜 香叶 大料 白蔻 小茴香
Green onion, ginger, bay leaf, white cardamom, fennel seed,
# 最关键的是在这儿 当归
and then here comes the most important thing, dong quai.
# 猪蹄下锅了啊 行了
Now we put the pork feet into the pot. Nice.
# 酒
Cooking wine.
# 冰糖老抽 这个颜色多好
Crystal sugar dark soy sauce. Such a wonderful color.
# 酱油 这真香
Soy sauce. - Smells so good.
# 酱油是提味的 老抽是上色的 一勺
The soy sauce here is to boost the taste, and the dark soy sauce is to enrich the color. - One spoonful.
# 颜色红亮
The color is red and bright.
# 再来几个枣 借借味
Put in a few red dates to give some taste to it.
# 你看见没有 煮了十来分钟了 面了
We have been cooking it for about 10 minutes. You can see it’s mushy now.
# 来点盐
Let’s add a bit of salt.
# （猪手）一上高压锅焖的时候
When the pork feet are being cooked in pressure cooker,
# 这芸豆您就关火闷着就行了
you can stop the heat for the kidney beans, put the lid on and let the residual heat further cook itself.
# 其实要自己家里吃 就没这么复杂了
Actually it can be simpler with a homemade version.
# 连这猪手剁好了之后
You can just chop the pork feet,
# 连枣带白芸豆一锅煮了
and cook it with the red dates and white kidney beans all in one pot.
# 往砂锅一盛就走了
Then you put everything into a casserole, and off you go.
# 咱这不是就想讲究点么
We are just making it sumptuous here.
# 比较事儿
We are being very particular about it.
# 现在当归还不会这么冲
So far the dong quai hasn’t released its strong smell.
# 待会您一进高压锅一压完了之后
Later when it’s cooked by the pressure cooker,
# 应该是当归的味在前对吧 对
the smell of dong quai should appear to be the top note, right? - Yes.
# 好 放到高压锅里头
Brilliant. Now we put everything into the pressure cooker.
# 大家看看这汤色 红亮
Check out the color of the soup, so red and bright.
# 好了
It’s ready for the pressure cooker.
# 高压锅 三十五分钟到四十分钟
In the pressure cooker for 35 to 40 minutes.
# 味道好极了
It’s going to be so delicious.
# 四十五分钟
Set the cooking time to be 45 minutes.
# 好了吧 压的时间到了
It should be ready. The time is up.
# 慢点慢点 大爷 太烂乎了
Be careful. Da Ye, it looks supremely mushy.
# 干脆就这么啃了得了
Why don’t we just keep it like this and gnaw at it.
# 一会我给您去骨吧
I’ll remove the bones for you.
# 您是定碗还是定盘啊 定碗啊大爷
Do you use a bowl or a plate as the mold, Da Ye?
# 我就跟外科大夫似的
I’m like a surgeon.
# 恰到好处
This is so perfectly cooked,
# 一提溜就出来
bones can be picked out effortlessly.
# 这是一劈两开
One chop easily splits it into two.
# 地道啊
How authentic.
# 这是一个面儿
This is the surface.
# 定碗就是有里儿有面儿
Using a bowl as the mold means there are a surface and a filling.
# 好了
It’s good now.
# 这个老佛爷真会吃
This empress mother really knows how to eat well.
# 我也会
I do, too.
# 看着啊 大芸豆煮的烂烂乎乎的
Look, those big kidney beans are now soft and mushy.
# 当归 泡好的当归
Dong quai, which is readily soaked.
# 再搁点葱姜
Let’s add a bit of green onion and ginger.
# 原汤 原汤一罐
Pour the original soup in.
# 好了
Fantastic.
# 锅开（蒸猪手）
When the water Boils, we start to steam the pork feet.
# 老佛爷会吃啊 半小时
Empress mother eats so well! Steam for half an hour.
# 到点儿了
It’s time.
# 这豆儿看蒸的 哎呦
Look at the steamed beans! Wow!
# 豆儿直动 跟木鱼花似的
The beans are moving, like katsuobushi!
# 葱姜 当归 咱也捡去
Let’s remove the green onion, ginger and dong quai.
# 这豆儿真动
The beans are really moving.
# 你看你看这个豆皮
Check out the skin of the white kidney beans.
# 忽扇忽扇的动 活了
It flaps as if it's alive.
# 把汤篦到碗里头 原汤啊
Now we filter the soup into a bowl. It’s the original soup.
# 先别掀盖
Do not remove the lid yet.
# 打打汁 原汁下锅
Let’s make some sauce. Put the original soup into the wok.
# 生粉勾芡  这点芡全进去了 正合适
Add the slurry. Perfect amount of slurry, all in.
# 来点熟油 搁这儿用勺子一碾
Now put in a bit of cooked oil, and then use the spoon to glide here.
# 齐活
Done!
# 红亮啊
Red and shiny.
# 老佛爷汁儿 老佛爷芡儿
Empress mother’s soup, empress mother’s sauce.
# 师父先吃 我不吃了 小亮吃吧
I’ll let my master eat first. - I’m fine not eating. Liang Zi, you can have it.
# 太好吃了
It tastes amazing.
# 坐着吃
You can take a seat while you have it.
# 这个菜得慢慢品
This is a dish to be enjoyed slowly.
# 您老人家坐着 老佛爷也讲究享受
You are sitting down, just like the empress mother enjoys being sumptuous.
# 您坐着我们站着 您吃着我们看着
You sit while we stand. You eat and we watch you eat.
# 享受老佛爷的待遇
I’m enjoying being treated like an empress mother.
# 这豆好吃 面
The beans taste so good, so mushy.
# 这豆太好吃了
The beans are superb.
# 这豆比那猪蹄还好吃
It tastes even better than the pork feet.
# 你看都黏碗儿
It even sticks on the bowl.
# 小亮这个好 小亮这个是整个一猪皮
Liang Zi is having a very good piece, a whole piece of pork skin.
# 我该说了啊
It’s my turn to comment now.
# 大爷说 大爷说我吃点这个
Please go ahead, Da Ye. I’ll just be eating this when you comment.
# 又来一块
Another piece!
# 爱吃就吃 好不容易逮着了
Eat as much as you like. Just seize the opportunity.
# 我就得按照评菜的标准来说
I’ll have to comment according to the dish evaluation standard.
# 那可就瞎了 不
That wouldn’t sound good. - No, it’s not like that.
# 首先颜色红亮 汁浓味厚 猪蹄软烂
First of all, it’s red and shiny in color. The sauce has a mellow taste and the pork feet is soft and mushy.
# 芸豆酥香 蒸的特别的透
The beans are smooth, aromatic and very thoroughly steamed.
# 枣香味浓
The dates are full of aroma and flavorsome.
# 然后当吃这爪尖的时候
When you eat the tip of the toe,
# 入口即化
it melts in your mouth.
# 小骨头秃噜秃噜全出来了
The little bones come out so smoothly.
# 很软烂
Very soft and mushy.
# 你看看烂不烂
Look how mushy it is.
# 就这块肉最好
This is the best piece of this dish.
# 其实我觉得二伯用当归用的特别巧妙
I really think Er Bai utilized dong quai in a very clever way.
# 虽然当归味很重
Although dong quai has quite a strong taste,
# 但是它不是很突出
it does not stand out.
# 这菜绝对是
This dish is
# 真好吃
really yummy.
# 二伯 点赞
Er Bai, a thumbs-up for you!